A Guide to the William W. Hurt Papers 1860-1929
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William W. Hurt Papers 1860-1929
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms92-025
2 containers; 0.7 cu. ft.
Business and personal financial papers of William W. Hurt, of Smyth and Washington counties, Virginia. Includes deeds, leases and other business and legal documents pertaining to several businesses, particularly the Douglas Land Company.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The William W. Hurt Papers were donated to the Digital Library and Archives in 1992. The collection was accessioned as the Douglas Land Company Records and was known by that title until 2005, when it was processed and renamed.
Biographical/Historical Information
William W. Hurt was born in Virginia around 1879. He married Zula Kinzer, and the couple had two sons: William Whitmore (1905-1984) and Fred Kinzer (1910-2003). The family initially lived in Washington County, but some years after becoming general manager of the Douglas Land Company, Hurt moved with his family to Marion (Smyth County), where he maintained an active interest in local affairs.
Many of Hurt's activities centered on his role as manager of the Douglas Land Company and in developing the company's holdings. He supervised the planting and operation of a commercial apple orchard, undertook game and fish conservation measures and built roads. Hurt was also involved in other business enterprises, many of which were probably connected--either directly or indirectly--with the Douglas Land Company. He served on the board of directors of the National Bank of Chilhowie and the Colonial Manufacturing Company; was vice-president of the Damascus Telephone Association and the Elk Garden Company and was president of the Smyth County Fair. Hurt died between 1916 and 1932.
The Douglas Land Company was organized in New York in 1904 to manage the Douglas family estate of Washington, Smyth and Grayson counties, Virginia. Under the management of William W. Hurt, the company developed timber, engaged in mineral prospecting and leased to local farmers lands from the estate, known as "Laurel Farm." In 1910, the company sold 28,000 acres of timberland to the United States government as a forest reserve. Timber from other tracts of land was sold to lumber companies. W. L. Umbarger succeeded Hurt as manager upon the latter's death; Umbarger was later succeeded by H. P. Gills. The company had ceased operation by 1932.
Source:
Wilson, Goodridge, Smyth County History and Its Traditions ([S.l.]: The Author, 1932).
Scope and Content
This collection contains the business and personal financial papers of William W. Hurt, of Washington and Smyth counties, Virginia. Records of the Douglas Land Company, of which Hurt served as general manager, comprise the larger part of the collection. These records consist primarily of lease agreements and deeds, as well as other contracts and legal documents.
The collection also contains records of several other enterprises in which Hurt was involved; at least some of these--such as the Laurel River Farm--were directly connected to the Douglas Land Company. The collection also contains items relating to the Colonial Manufacturing Company, Damascus Telephone Association, Elk Garden Company, Helton Company, Laurel River Lumber Company, and the Smyth County Fair Association.
Of Hurt's personal financial and legal papers, the collection contains several deeds and contracts into which he seems to have entered independent of his position with the Douglas Land Company.
The collection also contains a folder of documents--mostly receipts and doctor's prescriptions--belonging to J. B. Gilliam, a resident of Smyth County. Gilliam's connection to Hurt or the Douglas Land Company could not be determined while processing the collection.
A folder of general materials completes the collection and contains, among other items, various legal documents; 1922-1923 temperature and rainfall statistics for Marion, Virginia; a map showing a Douglas Land Company tract that was burned in a 1910 fire, and a copy of William Hurt's will.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by name of business, with Hurt's personal financial following the files devoted to specific businesses.
Contents List
- Colonial Manufacturing Company 1905-1906, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Damascus Telephone Association 1904, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Douglas Land Company leases
  - 1880-1893 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - 1894-1897 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - 1898-1903 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - 1904-1907 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - 1911-1929 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Douglas Land Company deeds
  - 1860-1907 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - 1908-1910 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - 1911-1919 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Douglas Land Company contracts
  - 1885-1908 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - 1909-1923, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Douglas Land Company legal documents 1904-1905, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
- Douglas Land Company survey calls 1905-1909, n.d. (Box-folder 1-15)
- Elk Garden Company 1912 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Helton Company 1907, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Laurel Farm financial records
  - 1921 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - 1922 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Laurel River Lumber Company 1904-1908 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Smyth County Fair Association 1914 (Box-folder 2-5)
- William W. Hurt personal deeds 1908-1916 (Box-folder 2-6)
- William W. Hurt personal contracts 1907-1912 (Box-folder 2-7)
- J. B. Gilliam papers 1893-1912, n.d. (Box-folder 2-8)
- Blank forms 1907-1915, n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)
- General materials 1873-1915, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  [see also Oversize Materials]
- Oversize Materials
  - "Map of the Douglas Land Company's 10712 Acre Patent Showing ... the Area Burnt Over by Fire ..." [1910]